Finding Aid for Robert P. Briggs Papers ca. 1890-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert P. Briggs Papers circa 1890-1981, 1942-1981
Briggs, Robert P., 1903-
5 oversize volumes
3.5 linear feet
University of Michigan professor of economics and accounting, businessman, U-M regent; papers include biographical material, topical files, correspondence, publications and speeches, audio-visual material, and scrapbooks.
861084 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection (Donor no. 2404 ) came to the library in 1981. Periodic additions have been received.
The collection is open for research.
Robert P. Briggs was born in Monroe, Michigan on April 3, 1903, the son of Rose Pierce Briggs and Robert D. Briggs. In 1908 his family moved to Lansing, Michigan and Robert Briggs completed his grade school education in the Lansing Public Schools. In 1920 he went to the University of Michigan and obtained both AB and MBA degrees in 1925 and 1928 respectively.
In 1927 Briggs accepted a position at the University of Michigan as an instructor in economics. He stayed in this position until 1935 when he was made assistant professor of economics and accounting. Briggs moved steadily though the ranks becoming associate professor in 1940 and full professor in 1945. Concurrent with his full professorship, Briggs was vice president of the University of Michigan in charge of business and finance. He resigned this post in 1951 and left the University to begin an executive career at Consumers Power Company in Jackson, Michigan which lasted until 1975.
Briggs held many offices and was a member of many boards during these years. Most notably, he was a member, vice-chairman, and chairman of the Board of Directors of the Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago from 1956 to 1964. He was the founding president of the Michigan State Chamber of Commerce in 1959. In 1964 he was appointed to the University of Michigan Board of Regents by Governor George Romney.
On December 22, 1925, Briggs married Maxine Eloise Corliss. The couple had two children, Ruth, born in 1933 and Peter, born in 1937.
The papers of Robert P. Briggs document aspects of his career as educator and administrator at the University of Michigan, and his experience as businessman and advocate for business. The papers are arranged in seven series: Biographical/Family Material; Topical files; Correspondence; Publications, Speeches, and Addresses; Audiovisual Material; and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Briggs, Robert Peter, 1903-; Education--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Briggs, Robert D.; Briggs family.; China.; Corliss family.; Enrico Fermi Nuclear Power Plant (Mich.); Food enterprises--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Food Service Building (University of Michigan); Harrison (Mich.); Offices--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration. Class of 1926.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration. Class of 1928.; Warehouses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Briggs, Robert D.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical/ Family Material
  The Biographical/Family Material contains information about Robert's long and varied affiliation with the University of Michigan. Also included are papers belonging to his parents and a 1897 diary belonging to his father.
  - Briggs, Robert P.
    - Biographical material (Box 1)
    - Oral history transcript 1992 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan
      - Committee to select president of the University of Michigan 1966-1967, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Faculty member (Box 1)
      - Honors received (Box 1)
      - Regent (Box 1)
      - Student (Box 1)
      - Vice-President (Box 1)
  - Other family members
    - Briggs, Robert D. (father)
      - Addresses and essays (Box 1)
      - Diary 1897 (Box 1)
    - Briggs, Maxine (wife); Terry and Adele Corliss (wife's parents) (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  Topical files is an alphabetical series documenting Robert Brigg's involvement with state politics, business, and the University of Michigan.
  - American Gas Association (Box 1)
  - Campaign for State Board of Education 1964 (Box 1)
  - Chamber of Commerce
    - Michigan State, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Common Market Committee 1966, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - China, University of Michigan delegation to 1977 (Box 1)
  - Conference of State Bank Supervisors (Box 1)
  - Consumers Power Company (Box 1)
  - Cooper Committee (Advisory Committee on Fiscal Organizations and Procedures) 1954 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Auto Labor Board (Box 1)
  - Detroit Ordnance District (Box 1)
  - Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago (Box 1)
  - Financial Institutions Bureau, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Impostor (Box 2)
  - Michigan United Fund (Box 2)
  - National Industrial Recovery Act (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    (see also scrapbooks in box 4 and oversize volumes 1-3)
  - Parsons, Donald H. (Box 2)
  - State Board of Accountancy (Box 2)
  - Traffic Safety Committee (Box 2)
  - Western Michigan University (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically in fifteen folders dating from 1941 to 1982 and pertains primarily to Briggs' business career.
  - 1942-1981 (scattered), 15 folders (Box 2)
- Publications, speeches and addresses
  The Publications, Speeches, and Addresses series is contained within sixteen folders from 1947 to 1973 and includes addresses to area high school graduating classes as well as an address to the University of Michigan graduating class of 1951. Also included in this series are speeches given at business conventions.
  - 1947-1973, 16 folders (Box 2)
- Audiovisual Materials
  The Audiovisual Material series contains photographs of Robert Briggs both as an adult and a child, cassette tapes of his life history which he completed in 1922, and several boxes of slides from his 1977 trip to China under the auspices of the University of Michigan.
  - Photographs
    - Briggs family (Box 3)
    - China, University of Michigan delegation to 1977 (Volume 4)
    - China, University of Michigan delegation to 1977 (Volume 5)
      (continued)
    - Consumers Power Company (Box 3)
    - Corliss family (family of Mrs. Briggs) (Box 3)
    - Federal Reserve Board, Chicago (Box 3)
    - Fermi Nuclear Power Plant (Box 3)
    - Groups (Box 3)
    - Michigan Financial Institutions Bureau (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (includes Harrison, Michigan) (Box 3)
    - Portraits (early to 1925) (Box 3)
    - Portraits (since 1926) (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan
      - Album, Food Service Building 1948 (Box 3)
      - School of Business Administration classes of 1926, 1928 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Slides
    - China 1977, 5 boxes (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan Buildings 1947 (Box 3)
  - Cassette tapes of oral history, 1992, 3 audiotapes (Box 3)
  - Motion picture, 2 film reels
    (each reel consists of footage from smaller numbered reels)
    - Reel 1 (containing reels 1-8) (Box 3)
      variety of family, picnic and vacation footage, brief footage of a UM football game, shot of an auto race? at a track adjacent to Chrysler Motors Building
    - Reel 2 (containing reels 9-15) (Box 3)
      (footage of train derailment at Michigan Central Station near Broadway Bridge (color) (near end of reel) and various shots of family activities and vacations
- Scrapbooks
  (numbered series; each volume includes index)
  Robert Briggs compiled Scrapbooks - the last series - to record University of Michigan events and personalities. There are seven scrapbooks which span the period of October 1944 to April 1958.
  - October 1944-May 1946 (Box 4)
    (Vol. I)
  - May 1946-January 1947 (Volume 1)
    (Vol. II)
  - January-October 1947 (Volume 2)
    (Vol. III)
  - November 1947-September 1948 (Volume 3)
    (Vol. IV)
  - September 1948-August 1950 (Box 4)
    (Vol. V)
  - August 1950-April 1952 (Box 4)
    (Vol. VI)
  - April 1952-April 1958 (Box 4)
    (Vol. VII)